<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good service hitherto ill rewarded, or, An historicall relation of eight yeers services for King and Parliament done in and about Manchester and those parts by Lieu. Col. John Rosworm.</title>
            <author>Rosworme, John, fl. 1630-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1996</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7314</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13230961</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13230961</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98599</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57684)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98599)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 437:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good service hitherto ill rewarded, or, An historicall relation of eight yeers services for King and Parliament done in and about Manchester and those parts by Lieu. Col. John Rosworm.</title>
                  <author>Rosworme, John, fl. 1630-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 41 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. [6].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rosworme, John, fl. 1630-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98599:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98599:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GOOD SERVICE HITHERTO ILL REWARDED. <hi>OR,</hi> An Hiſtoricall Relation of eight yeers Services for KING and PARLIAMENT done in and about <hi>Mancheſter</hi> and thoſe parts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Lieu: Col. JOHN ROSWORM.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Yeer, 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98599:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98599:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE HOUSE of COMMONS aſſembled in <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honorable Gentlemen:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His poore piece, would gladly begge an houre from You, at Your beſt leiſure; In it You will ſee the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed wrongs, and ſad Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities of a faithfull ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The honour of doing me juſtice is reſerved for You. When You read this, think ſuch a one Your Petitioner, as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors all faithleſſe and indirect courſes, and therefore muſt unavoidably periſh without Your ſudden ſuccour.</p>
            <p>It is in You to prevent what I cannot but fear; which done accordingly, the Earth ſhall not bear a more thankfull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer, than</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, John Roſworm.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98599:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98599:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE THOMAS Lord FAIRFAX, Generall of all the Forces in <hi>England</hi> and Ireland. <hi>OLIVER CROMWELL,</hi> Lieutenant Generall of the Armies. <hi>IOHN BRADSHAW,</hi> Lord Preſident of the high Court of Juſtice.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Would it were not my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happines to ſee the day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſhould trouble You with ſuch a ſad ſtory, as here I am bold humbly to preſent You. In it you will ſee, the faithfulneſſe of a Servant, the Rewards of his Service, the Extremities he is in, and his encouraged hopes of finding relief from you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98599:4"/>
His Petitions, I hope, will ſhortly find your eyes, or eares, or both: Oh let them not want your hearts, of which I cannot doubt, if your leiſure will ſuffer you to peruſe this naked Relation. I trouble you no more, but with this onely addition, that I ſhall be ever a moſt thankfull Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian of the reparation you ſhall afford me. And be,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt faithfull and humble Servant, John Roſworme.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 23. l. 19. <hi>Ratcliefs,</hi> r. <hi>Ratclief.</hi> p. 28. l. 8. unthenkfulneſſe, r. unthankfulneſſe. p. 37. l. 2. fram; r. from. p. 40. l. 7. that, r. to that. p. 40. l. 16. others: r. others?</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98599:4"/>
            <head>AN HISTORICALL Relation of Lieut: Coll: ROSWORMS Service and Rewards, ſince the firſt beginning <hi>of theſe Warres.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hen certainly, if ever, may a man ſpeak of his well done Services, when either a juſt Relation of them, may be the remedy of his preſent miſeries, or a feeble caſe of his over-burdened heart: both theſe at this time have an influence upon me; glad would I be, if the former end might prove ſucceſſefull. And truly why ſhould I not hope it? But if Equity and Reaſon hath left <hi>England,</hi> if I and mine muſt rot, ſtarve, periſh, famiſh, that have been a means to preſerve others from ſuch dreadfull ends, when they whom I ſerved, both can, and ſhould, and may, and that moſt eaſily, diſcharge their obligations to me, and therein ſuccour me. If it muſt be ſo, I ſhall yet
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98599:5"/>have a little eaſe in letting the world know both what I have done, and how I have been dealt with; in either of which if I blot one line with a falſhood, I make no queſtion, but ſome of my back-friends will labour to let as many ſee their teeth, as I defire may ſee the truth. Which as briefly and orderly as I can, I ſhall now begin.</p>
            <p>HAving at the beginning of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection upon juſt diſcontents forſaken that Kingdom, I came into <hi>England,</hi> and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> where I faſtened my ſtrangers home; I had not lived there three months, before the differences of this Kingdom were heightned into a War, and all parts were full of confuſion. The Town of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, apprehending a manifeſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ruine, from the Earl of <hi>Darby</hi> and his ſtrength, who appeared for the King; having none that knew what belonged to Military affairs, either for offence, or defence, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obſerved, and heard of me that I was bred up in Souldiery from my youth, well skilled in Fortifications, nor contemptibly furniſhed with all other military abilities: propounded and concluded with me a Contract under hand and ſeal, for half a yeer, engaging me by the utmoſt of my advice and skill, to endeavour the ſecurity of their Town, and engaging
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98599:5"/>themſelves, in conſideration of my ſervice for that time, to pay me 30 li. we agreed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. I muſt be bold to ſay, that my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of this Service (though for a poore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) as it was not ſmall in it ſelf; ſo it proved in the conſequents as conſiderable, both to the weakning of the Kings party, and the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Parliaments, as any action in that kinde, through the paſſages of that yeer: for (let it be conſidered) foure for one in that Town, if not more, favoured my Lord of <hi>Darby,</hi> and had publickly vowed to cut my throat, if ever I attempted any works to keep him out. The other party which favoured my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, were full of fears, and confuſions, not knowing which way to turn themſelves: the Town in all it's entrances, open, and without any defence about it; A powerfull Enemy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually expected to come upon them, which within three weeks of our Contract fell out: ſurely theſe were circumſtances, which might eaſily have made it lawfull to fear, and in that fear to decline a ſervice of this nature: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous to do the Town the beſt office, that either I could do, or they could wiſh, I put my life in my hand, I over-looked all dangers and difficulties, and undertook this Charge, which how I have diſcharged, let the world judge.</p>
            <p>By the way obſerve, that the very next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after my Contract, my Lord of <hi>Darby</hi> ſent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98599:6"/>two Gentlemen to me, with 150 <abbr>l.</abbr> as a Preſent from his Lordſhip, with an invitation to attend him at <hi>Latham.</hi> Twas eaſie to ſee, what the drift of this kindneſſe was. But 30 <abbr>l.</abbr> if backed with my promiſe, contract, or engagement, I have ever learned to value above all offers; honeſty being more worth than gold. Returning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my thanks for the Earls nobleneſſe, and the money with my thanks, I diſmiſſed theſe Gentlemen, and addreſſed my ſelf to my truſt.</p>
            <p>My firſt aime was to ſet up good Poſts and Chains, to keep out the Enemies Horſe; which by the contrivance of a falſe Alarum, and by the help of the Countreys coming in, upon the ringing of the Bels backwards, deviſed pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely for this end, I ſafely performed, though many tongues had doomed me to death, if ever I attempted it. This was done upon Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday the 22. of <hi>September,</hi> 1642.</p>
            <p>Having by this deviſe drawn ſome Armed men into the Town, I earneſtly preſſed, that they might be carefully provided for, heartned and encouraged; for I was confident, that within leſſe then a week, that the Enemy would make a reall approach, and then theſe men would ſtead us; they took my advice; and my prediction fell out accordingly.</p>
            <p>In that ſmall time of preparation which I had, I fortified and barricadoed up every ſtreets end, with the addition of Mud-wals, which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98599:6"/>were unfiniſhed when the Earl came upon us, I adviſed how our men ſhould be aſſigned through each part about the Town; But <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-bridge</hi> the onely place of manifeſt danger, greateſt action, and leaſt defence, upon others refuſall, I undertook my ſelf: though by my engagements I was not bound to fight at all, but to adviſe, and direct onely.</p>
            <p>For this ſervice, <hi>Septemb:</hi> the 28. I took with me 50. Muskettiers: we lay there till <hi>Munday</hi> without action.</p>
            <p>Munday, <hi>Septemb:</hi> 27. I was neceſſitated, to ſend 20. of my Muskettiers to Captain <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw</hi> at the Deanſ-gate which never returned: that afternoon, though thus weakened, I was numerouſly aſſaulted; but through the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of him, who ſaved us, my 30 Muskettiers (having no Breſt-work but a Chain) gave them a ſound repulſe.</p>
            <p>The next day, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 28. the Enemy plaid at us with his great Peeces, which being a ſtrange noiſe, and terrour to my raw men, ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen of them took their heels; the reſt, ſome for fear of my drawn ſword, others out of gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, reſolving rather to dye, than to forſake me, ſtuck cloſe to me, and to the ſafety of their Town. I was now few in number, but found ſome pitie from ſome other gallant hearts, who voluntarily came in to my aſſiſtance, making up my number 28. And this was my huge Army
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98599:7"/>even then, when I had not onely many Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies without, but dangerous temptations within to deal with. For the Enemy finding their aſſault not to take ſucceſſe, nor their Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons to terrifie us, as at the firſt, ſeverall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys ſore againſt my will, were ſent into the Town: whereof I gave my Souldiers a little notice, with incouragements to ſtand out, to the utmoſt.</p>
            <p>Particularly, Wedneſday, <hi>Septemb:</hi> 29. the Earl offered upon the delivery of ſome 100 Muskets to withdraw his Forces, and march away. To back this offer, Collonel <hi>Holland</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding my averſeneſſe, earneſtly preſſed me to condeſcend to the motion, uſing withall theſe three Reaſons. Firſt, ſaid he, we have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Powder nor Match. I confeſſe I had onely ſix pound of the one, and 18. fathome of the other; but this was onely known to my ſelf. Secondly, the Countreymen (ſaid he, though falſly,) will ſtay no longer, their own houſes and goods lying open to the mercy of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. Thirdly, ſaid he, the Enemy is increaſed in ſtrength. With theſe arguments did he not only urge, but almoſt command the embracing of the Earls Propoſals. I related theſe things to my Souldiers, who unanimouſly reſolving ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to yeeld to my Lord of <hi>Darby,</hi> ſo long as I would ſtand out, and they had an inch of Match, or a ſhot of Powder: my heart leaped
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98599:7"/>at ſuch courage, and thereupon I peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſed any terms whatever. Which ſo paſſionately moved Collonel <hi>Holland,</hi> that he left me in great anger and diſcontent. Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after this, Maſter <hi>Bourne,</hi> an aged and grave Miniſter, came down to the Bridge to me, I told him Collonel <hi>Hollands</hi> language, and the dangerous concernment it tended to, I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him, that if he deſired to prevent the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief which might enſue, he would immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walk to the Deanſgate, &amp; from thence to the other Centuries, uſing his beſt encouragements to prop up their hearts againſt any dangers; and aſſuring them from me, that whereas the Enemy now, made no aſſaults, but where I was, I was confident with the help of Almighty God, and my few men, to defend it againſt their whole Power, nor ſhould they ever enter at my guard. The heartned old man quickly left me, and followed my advice, with ſuch gravity and chearfulneſſe, that I cannot but aſcribe much to it, as to the means of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. Having thus prevailed for a refuſall of all terms, ſent in by the Enemy, our height of reſolution to defend our ſelves to the utmoſt was returned to the Earl; who finding by our actions that we ſpake as we meant, within 3. dayes after, withdrew this ſiege, and gave me leave with about ten of my men in open view, to fetch away a great number of good Arms from them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98599:8"/>
Thus was <hi>Mancheſter</hi> freed from the danger of her firſt brunt; wherein how farre I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall, if impartiall men cannot ſee, I will appeal from them to my Enemies; If either can deny me an acknowledgement, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the world ſhould be blinde, and what I have done ſhould be buried: But was the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> the whole of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? He that ſhall view in a Proſpective the ſtate of things at that time in the Kingdome, muſt yet ſee more, my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> had then at that inſtant no great Forces, and thoſe very remote from thoſe parts. And ſurely if the actions of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> had not ſufficiently ballanced the Earl of <hi>Darbies</hi> Forces, or had that Town yeelded either to his Aſſaults or Propoſals, <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and all thoſe aſſociated Counties, had been at his ſervice; and the whole Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dery therein at his diſpoſing; which with his own Souldiers would have made up at leaſt 9000 well armed fighting men, beſides Horſe. Theſe joyned to his Majeſties Body, who onely wanted Infantery, would have made ſuch an Army as in humane reaſon could not have found an oppoſition ſtrong enough from all the Parliaments Forces, which at that time could be brought together. Theſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I onely touch at, becauſe, though my heart would break, if I ſhould not let the world know, how I have ſerved, and am ſerved; yet I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98599:8"/>have no minde to draw my own picture. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one thing more let me adde, to do my ſelf a little right, ſince none elſe hitherto have done. This Town was not onely a foyl to an aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Enemy, but a ſtrength, help, and Magazine to all the adjacent Counties, as they ſtood en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged for the Parliaments ſervice. But of this enough.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Darby</hi> having afforded me a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy by his departure, I throughly ſet my ſelf to raiſe up my Works of Fortification about the Town, during the reſidue of that half yeer, for which my Contract was made: In which I did not onely proſecute that to my utmoſt, by my directions, but having declared my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that unleſſe we did ſomething ſpeedily againſt the Earl, he would get head again, and do us new miſchief: We thereupon gathered our Forces together, went out, and upon <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb.</hi> 24. we ſhattered the Enemy at <hi>Shewbent,</hi> and the ſame night we took <hi>Leigh</hi> by aſſault, returning again within three dayes.</p>
            <p>I was now ſo obſerved for my faithfulneſſe and ſucceſſe, that <hi>Januar.</hi> 2d. following I was unexpectedly honoured with a Commiſſion from my Lord <hi>Wharton,</hi> to be Lieutenant Coll: of a Foot Regiment to Coll: <hi>Aſhton,</hi> with which <hi>Febr.</hi> 6. I was commanded by Serjeant Major Generall <hi>Seaton,</hi> to joyne with Coll: <hi>Hollands</hi> Regiment, and to attempt <hi>Preſton,</hi> which was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98599:9"/>accordingly taken by aſſault, <hi>Febr.</hi> 8. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards at Serjeant Major Generall <hi>Seatons,</hi> and the Deputy Lieutenants requeſt, was forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by my direction.</p>
            <p>I kept this Command of Lieutenant Coll: during the reſidue of my half yeers ſervice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted for with the Town of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> which being now expired, they then obſerved, what they cannot without ſhame remember now, that I was both truſtie, and ſucceſſefull. They were loath to for-go ſuch a ſervant, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore propounded new terms to me, offering me an annuity of 60 li. <hi>per annum,</hi> to be paid 15 li. quarterly, during the lives both of my ſelf and wife, which ſhould ſurvive the longeſt, if I would by my advice proſecute the finiſhing of their Fortifications, and the ordering of all Military affairs conducing to the ſafetie of the Town, and upon all occaſions be ready to give directions accordingly. At the ſame time alſo they with the Deputy Lieutenants deſired me to accept of a Foot Company in the Garriſon of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> engaging themſelves to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, as long as it was a Garriſon, and to pay me 40 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 
               <hi>per</hi> week in part of my Captains pay, and the reſt was to go upon the publick Faith. I was preſſed to accept this ſo importunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on their part, and by one reaſon ſo ſtrongly within my ſelf, which was, that by embracing the firſt of theſe Propoſals, I ſhould not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98599:9"/>leave a deſolate Widow without a poore ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, in caſe a warlike end ſhould befall my ſelf, that I layed down my Lieutenants Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels Commiſſion, and cloſed with their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract; and is this circumſtance nothing to chain theſe men to their promiſes? Thoſe hearts cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly are deeply rooted in the Earth, which Reaſon, Equity, Conſcience, nay and ſhame cannot pull out with ſuch ropes.</p>
            <p>My Engagement being paſt, I returned to my Charge, enlarged my Fortifications, left nothing unprepared, as time would permit, which might not make an Enemy a ſtrong work to attempt me.</p>
            <p>Whileſt I was proſecuting theſe things, I was ſollicited, <hi>April</hi> the 1. 1643. by the Deputy Lieutenants to attend and aſſiſt our Forces, againſt <hi>Wigan;</hi> for indeed the Souldiers decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves diſcontented, if I went not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with them. I went accordingly, being loath that thoſe ſhould want any of my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, who had afforded me ſo much roome in their hearts; nor were we without a happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in our attempt, for by a gallant aſſault, chiefly of Collonel <hi>Aſhtons</hi> men, we took that ſtrong Town in leſſe than an houre: The Town being taken, to my beſt remembrance, we ſent 500 Muskettiers of Collonel <hi>Aſhtons</hi> men to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure <hi>Bolton,</hi> not far from us: Whileſt the Town was taken, the Enemy having for a refuge ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98599:10"/>and fitted the Church and ſteeple ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning for their advantage, fled thither as many as could, and killed from thence, I dare ſay, more men, after the taking of the Town, than we had loſt in the whole aſſault beſides. Whileſt we ſtruggled with this difficulty, an Alarum was ſent us from the Enemy, I went ſpeedily with ſome few Horſe to view the ſtate they ſtood in, I found them onely three ſlender troops of Horſe, who obſerving us to preſent a reſolute face towards them, they inſtantly tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their heels, and gave us language enough in their diſorder, to tell us we need not trouble our ſelves with ſuch Enemies. I returned with what haſt I could, with the truth in my mouth, but found Collonel <hi>Holland</hi> in ſuch a ſhaking agony of fear, that he was ready to march a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with all our Forces, conſiſting of 2000. Foot, moſt part good Muskettiers, the reſt Club and Bill men, and to my beſt remembrance about 200. or 300. horſe, beſides eight Piece of Ordnance, and no want either of Ammunition or proviſions. And ſurely with this Force I durſt have ſeen the face of the greateſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies we had about us, though conjoyned at that time. Having this confidence, I earneſtly deſired him not to leave that Garriſon ſo fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, that was won ſo gallantly; or if he would not ſtay himſelf, to leave me 500 Muskettiers, and one troop of Horſe, and clear me of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98599:10"/>Priſoners, of which we had already good ſtore, and I would entertain any attempt of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and proſecute the reſt of the ſervice touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Town, which was yet unfiniſhed. His Anſwer was, Stay, that ſtay would, he nor any of his men, either would or ſhould ſtay. I could almoſt have torn my fleſh at this anſwer; yet ſuppreſſing my paſſion, with deep intreaties, and repeated perſwaſions, he was at length wrought ſo farre, as to promiſe a ſtay till I had forced thoſe who had poſſeſſed the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Church ſteeple wholly to ſurrender; I having aſſured him, that I would either do it, or otherwiſe in one houre blowe them up: He gave me his hand to aſſure me of his ſtay. I thereupon firſt ſummoned them, but in vain. I prepared for execution, the event whereof ſtartling the Enemy, they all ſurrendred, being 86. in number. But whileſt I was receiving their Arms, and making preparation for their Convoy, Collonel <hi>Holland</hi> (for, alas, who can ſettle a trembling heart?) marched away with all the Forces, left me with one Company one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (theſe alſo, fearing their inabilitie to deal with ſo many priſoners, forſaking me) engaged amongſt 400 priſoners, many good Arms, two great Peeces of Ordnance, in the middeſt of a Town where generally all the Townſ-people were great Malignants. Being thus wholly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken by all, I was forced firſt to run to finde
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98599:11"/>Horſe, and then to flie for my life, which in ſuch a danger was moſt ſtrangely ſaved.</p>
            <p>All that adhered to the Parliament through the whole Kingdome, and knew the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of this aſſault, rejoyced at the taking and ſuppoſed keeping of <hi>Wigan,</hi> as a confider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſervice; It being thought an impregnable piece, the Enemies pride, and our fear; onely Collonel <hi>Holland</hi> ſeemed to be troubled that I periſhed not in the action; and therefore find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I ſurvived his treacherie in leaving me in the midſt of ſo many enraged Enemies, as I before ſhewed; did the beſt he could to deſtroy me and my family a worſe May. For preſently upon the taking of that Town, as a noble gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity for that ſervice, and yet ſaving my own life, the 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> 
               <hi>per</hi> week as part of my Captains pay (the onely main pillar of my family ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences) was by Collonel <hi>Hollands</hi> command, ſubſcribing 2 hands more for the countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of his unworthineſſe, taken away from me, upon this pretence, that I had not taken the Covenant, and was ſuſpended for above a yeer; during all which time notwithſtanding, I was ſtill kept in my employment.</p>
            <p>I cannot forget that about that time, and many times ſince, I received ſeverall Letters of acknowledgement from ſome eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Kingdom, but I could feed neither my dog, nor my cat with them, much leſſe my
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98599:11"/>horſes, which I have kept alwayes at my own expences in the ſervice, though afterwards up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſecond thoughts ſome of my charges were allowed me: but as for my family, who could not live upon the bare return of my expences, I was compelled to trie an unhappy experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether I could feed them with I thank you. But enough of this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wigan</hi> ſervice done, and undone, for which I was payed accordingly, I came to my charge at <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> whence not long after I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to ride to <hi>Lever-pool,</hi> to direct the Fortiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations there, I ſtayed there five dayes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>March</hi> 11. after my return thence, I, beſides many more out of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> and the County, was ſummoned up by Warrant to attend the Committee of Examinations upon the 15. of <hi>April</hi> next after, and to give in our Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons touching Collonel <hi>Hollands</hi> actions, where all this, and divers things more were juſtified to his face, as his perfidious dealings at <hi>Wigan,</hi> his actions touching Mr. <hi>Peter Heywood</hi> and his ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſſe in urging me to deliver up <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> when I kept <hi>Salford bridge,</hi> at the firſt. But his great friends in the houſe prevailed for his eſcape, accounting it perhaps a ſufficient pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment that he was ſo publickly ſhamed. Whereas if I had been guilty of the like, I am ſure the Law of Armes would have condemned
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98599:12"/>and executed me for bad ſervice, that am ſought to be famiſhed for good.</p>
            <p>About <hi>July</hi> 4 after, the Earl of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> with no ſmall Force made an angry approach towards <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> our men were ſent out to oppoſe his paſſage, nor was I thought fit to be preſent at this action: The iſſue was, our men were ſoundly beaten at <hi>Wicked-hill</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> and purſued into <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> by the Enemy, who quickly alſo poſſeſſed himſelf of <hi>Hallifax,</hi> about 16. miles diſtant from us. When I had received this ſad intelligence, I informed my ſelf of the nature of the paſſes, by which the Enemy moſt eaſily could come in upon us; and finding them capable of a ſudden Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the conſent of the Deputy Lieutenants, I quickly helped Nature with Art, ſtrengthning <hi>Blackeſtone Edge,</hi> and <hi>Blackegate,</hi> and manning them with Souldiers, to prevent the Earls dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous approach, by which means being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, like an angry ſtorme with a guſt, he went to the ſiege of <hi>Hull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How conſiderable this diverſion of ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full an Enemy was, let reaſon judge; for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, whereas he never reached his end at <hi>Hull,</hi> if he had gotten in amongſt us, we were not onely in a manifeſt danger of being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run by an enraged Enemy, but all parts within an ordinary diſtance, would have felt the ſmarting bitterneſſe of his heavy hands.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98599:12"/>
1643. <hi>Jan.</hi> 19. following, I received order from Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> to accompany his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the relieving of <hi>Nantwitch,</hi> at that time cloſely beſieged by the Enemy. Where how I diſcharged the truſt repoſed in me, I leave to the teſtimony of his Excellency, whoſe name I ſhall alwayes remember with honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nantwitch</hi> relieved, I repaired to my home, where I have with my utmoſt skill nouriſhed a company of vipers, who in recompence would eat my bowels.</p>
            <p>From thence I was once more, <hi>Aug.</hi> 16. 1644. commanded by Sir <hi>John Meldrum</hi> to attend him to the ſiege of <hi>Leverpoole,</hi> which continued full ten weeks, I there ſerved as Maſter of the Ordnance, gave directions for divers Works. In a word, I failed not in any thing which could be expected from me during the ſiege, it was ſurrendred <hi>Novemb.</hi> 4. For all which, and many other ſervices, I am to this day unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded.</p>
            <p>And now I come to my laſt actions, not a little conducing to the great ſhame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and the farther eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of my own honeſty.</p>
            <p>After the ſiege of <hi>Leverpoole,</hi> the Parliament with a great Force layed ſiege to <hi>York;</hi> to raiſe this ſiege, Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> made an haſtie and a furious march, with a very great Army; ſo that from the beginning of theſe Wars, there were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98599:13"/>not two ſuch numerous Armies, nor ſo fiercely reſolved each againſt other, as met at length upon the occaſion of that ſiege; Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> well noting, that there were two wayes to raiſe this ſiege, which was the whole of his work and deſigne; the one by policy, the other by force, left neither unattempted; His politicall method lay no where ſo ſtrongly for his end, as to corrupt me for the betraying of <hi>Manche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> wherein had he ſped, <hi>Yorke</hi> ſiege would have raiſed of it ſelf. To effect this, Prince <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert</hi> joyned my Lord <hi>Byron</hi> to himſelf in the tranſactions; and having the advantage of one Mr. <hi>Peter Heywood,</hi> by his means laboured with me for the betraying of the Town.</p>
            <p>This Mr. <hi>Peter Heywood,</hi> who at this time ſits at his eaſe, and enjoyes his own, whileſt I for want of it endure extreme miſerie: was a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> for the Parliament, was often in our private conſultations; and by holding intelligence with the Enemy, did us much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief. He went oft to <hi>Cheſter, Oxford,</hi> and other Garriſons of the Enemie, diſcovering our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret reſults. This being at length found out, and proved againſt him, he was ſecured by the Committee; and yet, without the conſent of the reſt of the Committee, contrary to an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance touching ſuch caſes, releaſed by Coll: <hi>Holland;</hi> two of his friends alſo being bound for his appearance, which never were queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98599:13"/>though he preſently upon his enlargement went to the Enemy, &amp; was afterwards thought the onely fit inſtrument to work me to this treacherie.</p>
            <p>His method was, firſt to take advantage of the injurious and moſt unthankfull unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which the Town had uſed towards me, ſtirring thoſe paſſions in me, which he knew were deeply provoked. This done, he offered in the behalf of Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> that I ſhould have a very great ſumme of money payed me in my hand, before my delivery of the Town, that I ſhould have great preferments under Prince <hi>Rupert;</hi> beſides the perpetuall obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of affection and honour from many moſt noble friends, which I ſhould look upon as pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by the deſert of ſuch a ſeaſonable and uſefull ſervice.</p>
            <p>I was not ſo little a fool, though I never meant to be a knave, but I gave the propounder audience, gave ſome incouragement to the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, ſo much as to fiſh out which way the Enemy would lay his ſtratagem, and to ſecure my ſelf from ſuſpicion on their part, appointed them a time of receiving their hopes. And I muſt needs ſay, I could with more eaſe have ſold them, man, woman and childe, with all they had into their Enemies hands, than at any time I could have preſerved them. But, alas, I ſhould then have been a <hi>Mancheſter</hi> man, for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98599:14"/>never let an unthankfull man, and a promiſe-breaker, have another name.</p>
            <p>When I had found out the bottome of the plot, and ſearched out the method of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; Immediately I ſent for ſix of the chief men of the Town, layed open the whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, told them how to prevent the danger, laboured night and day to get our Cannons to the Work, repaired our Mudwals, as well as time would ſuffer. In a word, left nothing uncared for, which was neceſſary to entertain an aſſault. But the Enemie having got ſome intelligence of our actions by our treacherous friends, or home-bred enemies, when he had marched within one or two miles of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> at his appointed time, having notice of an hot entertainment, inſtead of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> ſteared his courſe another way.</p>
            <p>I muſt not forget here a new peece of wrong, <hi>Mancheſter</hi> and the whole Kingdom received from Coll: <hi>Holland</hi> at this time, that very mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which I had diſcovered the plot, Coll: <hi>Holland</hi> had ſummoned the Souldiers of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Hundred, conſiſting of almoſt 4000 Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettiers to my beſt remembrance. He was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by us at <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> that theſe Souldiers might quarter in or near the Town, that they might aſſiſt us in times of danger: But how were we anſwered? he disbanded theſe men, went away, left us to our ſelves, there being no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98599:14"/>eſtabliſhed Souldiers in the Town at that time: but that one ſingle Company under my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and ſome few of Major <hi>Radliffs</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, which, with all that could be perſwaded to look to the ſecurity of their lives and liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, made not up ſo many Muskettiers, as to double our guards, much leſſe reaſonably to enable us againſt a reſolute Enemies at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. Nor was our diſtreſſe without many aggravating circumſtances, for beſides the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of our Mudwals, and the unmounting of our Cannons, we knew not who to truſt. The inſinite toyl, pains, and indefatigable induſtry, night and day, which I uſed at this time, all that had eyes in that Town ſaw, and all that have tongues can witneſſe; inſomuch that the ableſt, and richeſt of thoſe who had engaged themſelves for my Annuity, being overcome with the conſideration of my pains, and the ſhining evidences of my fidelity, gave me deep proteſtations and promiſes, That if ever the hand of Providence ſhould lead them to peace again, and that Trading might once again flouriſh, they would out of their own private purſes, enlarge my reward; particularly foure of the ſix to whom I firſt diſcovered the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſtratagem, ſpecified their ſummes. Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> promiſed me 10 li. Mr. <hi>Gaskell</hi> 20 li. Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> 30. Mr. <hi>Hartley</hi> 40 li. yeerly, as long as I lived. But, alas, when our diſtreſſe was over,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98599:15"/>which laſted a week, this ſmoke vaniſhed. The iſſue was this, that whereas Coll: <hi>Holland</hi> (who ever hath been (as you may ſee all along) the bountifull rewarder, encourager, and furtherer of my good ſervices) had ſuſpended my 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> 
               <hi>per</hi> week, part of my Captains pay, for a whole yeer, they drew a moſt importunate Petition to the Houſe, for the Arrears of my pay, and continuance of it, for the time to come; recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending me alſo for ſome noble gratuity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to my deſerts and quality. This Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion begot me an Order for my diſcontinued pay, and a recommendation from the Houſe to <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> for my Annuity: It was dated, <hi>Sept.</hi> 4. 1644. This being granted me, through much importunity, and great expences on my part, my 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> 
               <hi>per</hi> week was payed me till <hi>Octob.</hi> 9. 1647.</p>
            <p>I ſhall onely adde one more Evidence of my faithfulneſſe to this ungratefull Town. The Summer after Prince <hi>Ruperts</hi> diverſion, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to lay his heavy hand of plague upon us, which, ranging according to his direction, left no part unviſited; becoming indeed ſuch a ſad object, that our very miſeries were as great a guard to us againſt our Enemies, as the cries of them were ſtrong for a publick commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from our friends. The Peſtilence in a little time grew ſo hot, that it not onely occaſioned moſt of the richeſt to depart with their whole
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98599:15"/>families, but moved alſo the Warden and the other Miniſter to deſire me with my family to withdraw not far from the Town, that, if occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion were, I might from thence readily ſerve the danger and extremitie, which might befall it from the Enemie: I think few men would have blamed me, if having ſtayed thus long, I had left the Town upon ſuch importunitie. But conceiving my ſelf as ſtrongly tyed to look to the goods and eſtates of thoſe that were gone, as one of the Miniſters thought himſelf char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to look to the ſouls of thoſe there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; I waved all fear, and reſolved perſonally to ſerve my truſt, leaving my death to him, that once gave, and often before had ſpared my life. And truly my reſolution herein, I muſt be bold to ſay, was not a little courteſie to this Town; as both I foreſaw how things would, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards did come to paſſe. For Major <hi>Ratcleifs</hi> and his Company having withdrawn, and quartered themſelves without the Works for fear of the plague, my ſelf having onely 12. Muskettiers, whoſe hearts ſtood fixed to run my hazard, the poore, many of whom were at the peſt-houſes without, and the reſt within, entred into a dangerous combination, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a dozen of the middle ſort of men, that were within, to take advantage of our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and nakedneſſe, and to ſeize upon the whole riches of the Town, which at that time
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98599:16"/>was very great. In the proſecution of this vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, they wanted neither ſecreſie, unanimity, nor craft. Not ſecreſie, for till their deſigne was ripe, I had no knowledge of it; which argues alſo their unanimity. As for their craft, a man would have thought ſome minor Jeſuite had been of their counſell. They had prepared, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, a kinde of Declaration, zeal to the ſafety of the Town, ſolicitouſneſſe to ſee it ſo naked, and unfit to oppoſe an Enemy, were the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered coat of this pretty brat; and to make up all, they added a reſolution to ſlick to King and Parliament, and to uſe the whole fruits of their attempts to ſerve the Publick: and I, forſooth, had the honour to be nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their chief Commander. I had at this time taken phyſick, but my Serjeant, Mr. <hi>Beirom</hi> the elder, having diſcovered the plot to ſome in the Town, who quickly came to adviſe with me. We with ſome few others, which we ſent for, agreed upon this as the ſuddeneſt remedy, that the twelve chief conſpirators ſhould be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally ſent for into one roome, at one time, and afterwards ſeverally examined, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly was done; their examinations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſtill upon fyle in <hi>Mancheſter.</hi> Whileſt theſe things were doing, I gave order for my 12 Muskettiers privately to attend me, with whoſe aſſiſtance having ſecured theſe heads, the conſpiracie vaniſhed into ſmoke, which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98599:16"/>otherwiſe would have ſet all on fire.</p>
            <p>The plague being ceaſed, and the chief in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Town returned, a man would have thought that this laſt Evidence of my faithfulneſſe alone, ſhould have wrought theſe men, if not to thankfulneſſe, yet to honeſty: But who can vvhite a Blackmore? or make a rope of ſand? Their brows vvere braſſe to all intreaties, their affections flints to all reaſon, their hearts rocks to all pitie, and their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences adamants to all obligations, even ſtill my Annuity vvas kept from me; vvhich ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravating my many debts and vvants to the height of extremitie, in hope of relief I repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>London.</hi> Where prevailing not for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe, in three quarters of a yeers attendance, vvith my boy and tvvo horſes, at very great expences; at length (it being true, that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter artis ingenii<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> largitor venter,</hi>) it came into my head, to print an angry Paper, the Copie vvhereof I have here inſerted.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="complaint">
               <body>
                  <head>A ſad Complaint of Lieutenant Collonel John Roſworme, againſt ſeverall of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of Mancheſter.</head>
                  <p>I Poſt and ſend abroad this to the deſerved ſhame of the Tovvnſmen of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> vvhoſe names are under-vvritten, vvhoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh, moſt unvvorthy and perfidious deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98599:17"/>if I could, I would publiſh to the end of the world: My complaint is this, let all Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers judge, When the Town of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> at the beginning of theſe Wars, was in a moſt deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate danger and extremitie by reaſon of the Enemie, I (who have been a known Souldier in Forrain parts) was then looked upon as a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable man for the ſafety and preſervation of that Town, and was accordingly compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with, by thoſe under-written in the towns behalf, to fortifie the ſaid Town, and, in a word, to mannage all Military affairs tending to their ſafety and preſervation: In conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which, they obliged themſelves under hand and Seal, to pay me quarterly, every quarter of a yeer 15. li. during the lives of my ſelf or wife, which ſhould live longeſt; adding with all ſuch Solemn Proteſtations and Vowed Engagements of farther thankfulneſſe, that, conſidering their profeſſion of holineſſe above other men, it might eaſily have wrought an hope in a credulous man, that they would be more then honeſt. But all that gliſtered was not gold; for ſee the iſſue. I diſcharged my En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements to the utmoſt of a man, yea to the utmoſt of their hopes. Their Town was ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, themſelves preſerved, through Providence, my great pains, induſtry, and uncorrupted Faithfulneſſe. In the proſecution of my truſt, I incurred frequent and moſt manifeſt dangers
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98599:17"/>of my life, from which my eſcape hath been a matter both of their wonder, and their joy; of all which I have their own acknowledgements to produce, and teſtifications of their thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe ſo deep, as if they had looked upon me, as the onely earthly Landlord of their lives: All this notwithſtanding, theſe men (if they deſerve ſo good a name) conceiving themſelves to have no other uſe of me, have for this 12. moneths with-held from me my dearly earned ſtipend, broken their Covenants, ſlighted their Engagements, oppoſed all fair motions, and frequent entreaties of my own, refuſed all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall exhortations, earneſtly and often preſſing their dutie herein upon them; deſpiſed all requeſts and letters of publick and private eminent perſons, not onely minding them of, but reproving them for their backwardneſſe, I may ſay perfidiouſneſſe; ſo that, if I were not beholding to a more bountifull Providence, then what runs in their honeſty, I and mine might rot, periſh, ſtarve or famiſh, whom by their obligation, as well as the Common ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations of Equitie, they are bound to relieve; what ingratitude this is, let the world judge; yea, judge your ſelves, ye worſt of men; did I hazard life, limbs; and all that was dear to me, and do the richeſt of you grudge me a few ſhillings by the yeer, to buy me and mine food: is this your equitie? have you ingaged your
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98599:18"/>ſelves ſolemnly for my ſatisfaction, and now do you deny it me to my deſtruction; Is this your honeſty? would you indeed murder me, my wife and children after the higheſt manner of cruelty, that under God have been a means of preſerving you alive? What? is no other death ſit for me but famiſhing? have you no eaſier way to ſhew your unthenkfulneſſe then that? are you ſo hard-hearted to a ſtranger, ſo perfidious to your obligation, ſo unthankfull for curteſies, ſuch obſtinate enemies of reaſon and equitie? do you profeſſe your ſelves aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſee me, and can you read this without bluſhing; ye Adamants, can ye indeed be ſo flintie? Well, be ſo for ever, finde out the utmoſt bounds of ingratitude, be matchleſſe in your treacherie; ſet the Devill himſelf a Copie, that you may be the moſt infamous men of your generation, and when you have done, triumph in this; That your Conſciences are made of ſuch ſteel, as can be touched with nothing. As for me, the utmoſt of your cruelty, ſhall I hope, reach no farther then to cauſe me to be angry with my ſelf, that I have ever hazarded my blood for ſuch deſpicable earth-worms: But withall let me tell you, I hope I ſhall finde out a way to make you pay me againſt your wills, nor ſhall your diſhoneſtie for ever help you.</p>
                  <p>To conclude (for I know though your brows be Baſilſico-proof, yet you could be content, I
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98599:18"/>ſhould end this Language;) if ever you ſtand in need of the faithfulneſſe of a man again, may you meet with none that will truſt you, better then you deſerve, for ſince you have in my caſe, manifeſted your beſt profeſſion to be but helliſh diſſimulations, what man after me, will ever credit you? who will ever free me from this reproach of being the laſt credulous fool that ever you ſhall abuſe? If any thing here ſeem either to your ſelves or others too ſharp, I ſhall ſhortly cleer your eye-ſight, and preſent you, with a larger Looking-glaſſe wherein you ſhall ſee (if you will not ſhut your eyes) Circumſtances enough, which will more fully diſcover your bruitiſhneſſe not onely to your ſelves, but to all that will take the pains to obſerve your moſt deteſtable unworthineſſe, ſo farewell.</p>
                  <p>The Names of thoſe unworthy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-breakers in <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> who have ſealed and ſubſcribed the Covenant in behalf of themſelves and the whole Town</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich: Heyrick</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will: Radelyff</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich: Haworth</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rouland Hunt</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Hartly</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Gaskell</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho: Lancaſhire</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Lomax</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Johnſon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lawrence Owen</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Lewer</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nich: Hawet</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98599:19"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edw: Holbroock</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roger Worthington</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Meare</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>henry Bradſhowe</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Ellingworth</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mich: Buxton</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rap. Wollen</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hugh H Williams</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Dean</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Mynſhall.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Lond:</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>May 9. 1648.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The ſhame of this Paper, which the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my condition, and the unworthines of their dealing, forced me to Print, together with the concurrence of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> advance, from which they feared danger, occaſioned them to recall me from <hi>London,</hi> and to pay me my then Arrears.</p>
            <p>But this ſtorme being over, they again moſt ſhameleſly ſlighted their Engagements; and therfore being utterly worn out with the vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their uſage, and finding nothing to work, I ſent them a Letter dated, <hi>Octob.</hi> 11. 1648 deſiring their leave that I might ſeek imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment where I could, and look after a means of ſubſiſtence elſewhere, ſince their hearts were ſuch, that they could ſuffer me, my wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and family to periſh before their eyes, who for ſix or ſeven yeers had been an evident Inſtrument of keeping them, their wives and children from the ſame end. For this purpoſe I ſent them incloſed the form of a teſtimony to be ſubſcribed; the reſult of all was, I neither could get pay, nor teſtimoniall: what is this, but as much as to ſay in other words, For all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98599:19"/>the good ſervice you have done us, we will keep you here, and famiſh you?</p>
            <p>I have now done my ſtory, what's behinde muſt be for Application. And firſt I ſhall begin with thoſe undertakers of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> who firſt engaged me; and firſt, and laſt, and all along, have almoſt equalled my ſervices with their wrongs.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Maſters.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>For it hath been my unhappineſſe to have been your ſervant. Give me your leave a little.</p>
                  <p>(If you have any roome in your memories for any thing but debts) you may well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the confuſions, fears, and extremities, you were in, when you firſt deſired my ſervice; what a ſtrong Enemy you expected from without, how divided within, how weakly provided, and unable againſt either; inſomuch that my Engagement in your ſervice, was as much the wonder of your Enemies, as the preſervation of your ſelves ſo far as may be aſcribed to a means. Having undertaken your ſervice, you may remember, if you pleaſe, the dangers I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed my ſelf to, beyond my covenant, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers which I refuſed from many, the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties I ran through, the vigilancy and care which I uſed, the faithfulneſſe which I diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, my ſticking to your eſtates during the plague, when moſt of you (which was ſtrange) forſook them your ſelves; and the ſucceſſe of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98599:20"/>all through my whole ſervice. You may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member too, what me thinks you have forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that I had your hands and ſeals for a poore annuity, beſides the voluntary additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall promiſes from ſome of you, of 10 li. from another, 20 li. from another, 30 li. from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, 40 li. yeerly as long as I lived, flowing from the ſenſe of my care, and faithfulneſſe, once viſible in <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> but now removed beyond the <hi>Indies.</hi> But, I pray you, my maſters, ſuffer your ſervant to reaſon with you: Was I once thought worthy of ſo much? And now have I not deſerved my poore wages of you? that have kept for ſome of you ſuch vaſt eſtates? Do you ſtill grudge me the yeerly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of a few ſhillings, that have kept for you ſo many pounds, ſo many thouſands? Have I expoſed my ſelf for your ſafety, to the danger of ſword, and plague, and will nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent your boundleſſe ingratitude, unleſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all you throw me and my whole family into the jaws of famine? You have been thought men of conſcience, why could no miniſteriall exhortations prevail with you, often propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and urged upon you for that purpoſe? You have profeſſed your ſelves the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments devoted ſervants, why was their recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation ſlighted? You would not be thought uncivill, why were my Lord Generals Letters ſo little regarded? You would not be reported
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98599:20"/>as ſhameleſſe, why did ſhame force you to a piece of your duty, upon the ſight of my print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Paper inſerted before? whereas now again like the dogge, you are turned to your vomit. You complain of others for want of juſtice, why have you uſed ſo little to me? You pretend a great deal of care of your credit, why have you ſuffered your words, hands, and ſeals to be wounded? Religion bids you be courteous to ſtrangers, why have you dealt thus unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, yea moſt cruelly with me? who though a ſtranger, have been more then a brother, and have then ſtuck to you, when for fear you have fled from your ſelves. Equity, reaſon, yea ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love, requires you to be thankfull for courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, having forgotten all theſe obligations, I favour you too much if I ſay you are out of your wits, for then you will be ſomewhat excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; whereas, if you will be thought other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, you cannot. When your fears had ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred you heartleſſe, my undertaking your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and lively incouragements revived you; when you have been compaſſed with your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, my ſervice hath been your freedome; when you have ſlept, I have been watching for you; when you have ſtretched your ſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſoft beds, I have made the cold earth my lodging; when inſtead of cloaths to keep me warm, I have been wet round with the rain; I did not envy theſe things to you, I did not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98599:21"/>theſe things for you. I might ſay much more, if I were not reſolved to have this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of you to be able juſtly to ſay, I might have ſaid more if I pleaſed.</p>
                  <p>But how have you dealt with me? When in my diſtreſſes I have made my moan to you for my dearly earned ſtipend, your ears were deaf, your hearts pitileſſe, my wife and children could not finde the way to your boſomes, though you and yours have not wanted large roome in mine? What was your meaning, were you ambitious to be the moſt notable men in all the earth for cruell unthankfulneſſe? If ſo, I will do my beſt to procure you the honour, as far as my few languages will reach, you ſhall not fail; or was it becauſe in your actions to me you would ſhew your ſelves honeſt men? You have done it indeed, ask your conſciences elſe, and they will tell you ſo; becauſe none elſe will: Or was it your purpoſe to force me to flie the Kingdom, and to leave my wife, and children to your Pariſhes charitie, when both the husband of that wife, and the father of thoſe children could finde ſo little of your ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, equitie or honeſtie? Perhas 'twas this: but yet me thinks having ſome ſubtiltie of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, you might have thought, that he that was no traitor to your bowels, would not be a traitor to his own. Sure then your ayme was I ſhould be driven to rob by the high-way,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98599:21"/>and violently to take from others, what ſhould be the ſupport of my familie. And yet me thinks you could not think this, ſeeing you well knew that I have ever been carefull of my honeſtie even to you, who have failed to me? how then ſhould I be injurious to ſuch, whom perhaps I have never ſeen, when I have not wronged you, that have ſo ſore provoked me? You know I have ever laboured to keep others from plundering, how then ſhould I practiſe it my ſelf? But perhaps you are ſtill of that judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment however you uſe me, that certainly ſome miracles would be manifeſted from heaven, before a man that had ſerved you ſo faithfully ſhould want, though you ſhould give me no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: If theſe were your thoughts, then by your confeſſion, I muſt look for miracles, before you will be honeſt; and if that follow after, 'twill be the greateſt miracle of all: if none of theſe are right gueſſes, for my part I am at a loſſe, help me out, and then you ſhal hear move; till then I leave you.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Having done with theſe, I ſhall keep that order in my debates, which I obſerve in my wrongs. <hi>Mancheſter</hi> was firſt, and the <hi>Parliament</hi> in its late ſtate was next, to them muſt I be bold to ſay a little.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98599:22"/>
                  <head>To the Honorable Houſe of COMMONS, ſitting till the yeer 1648. and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Members for <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honorable Gentlemen:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOu need not be put in minde, I hope, that whatſoever I did for <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> reacht at length to your ſelves, &amp; from you to the whole Kingdom; It hath been eaſie for many impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall eyes to ſee, that my actions at <hi>Mancheſter</hi> in the beginning were the verie hinges, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the War turned; for had not my Lord of <hi>Darbies</hi> Forces been boldly oppoſed, and at length utterly cruſhed, by the activity, bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſucceſſe of thoſe Forces, with which I alwayes perſonally ſerved (where mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf alone, I deſire not to rob any other of their due honour) half an eye may ſee in humane reaſon, what condition you had been brought to, ſucceſſe at firſt being that which both animated, and encreaſed your friends.</p>
                  <p>I muſt not here forget, any point of right or honour which was ſhewed me, for I ſuppoſe that publick teſtimony, which was given of my ſtirring, vigilancy, faithfulneſſe, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe begot me unexpectedly my Lord <hi>Whartons</hi> Commiſſion to be Lieutenant Collonel to Coll: <hi>Aſhton.</hi> Which command how I uſed, till I layed it down, I have touched before, and can confidently leave to any that knew my
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98599:22"/>actions. But I beſeech you forgive me, if as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly as freedome forced fram miſery, will give me leave, I ſpeak ſomething alſo of yours.</p>
                  <p>Having laied down my Commiſſion of Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Collonel, I degraded my ſelf into a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain, that I might be the fitter to diſcharge my truſt to <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and to attend your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice there, where it was of moſt concernment. I was content to take 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> 
                     <hi>per</hi> week in part of my Captains pay, and the reſt upon the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith; and this with the poore addition of my <hi>Mancheſter</hi> annuitie, was the whole live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of my wife, children and family. But as <hi>Mancheſter</hi> ſuſpended the one, ſo your ſelves at length ſuſpended the other; upon which being deprived of all means of ſubſiſtence, I addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed two Petitions to your Houſe, all which were worn out in ſome of your pockets, and my ſelf at length after almoſt 12. months ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, diſmiſſed with this, That my Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was but a private buſineſſe, from a private man, and the Parliament would not look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; but yet I muſt acknowledge, I was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed from you a little money, not ſo much as would bear my charges of attendance.</p>
                  <p>Forgive me now a little freedome, when I did you ſervice, I was a publick man, was I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered becauſe I came in my great miſeries to petition for my wages? eſpecially having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born you ſo long, that I ranne in debt for the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98599:23"/>bread which I did eat, as ſtill I do? Or if I were not that <hi>Roſworme</hi> which ſerved you, as active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, faith fully, and ſucceſſefully as any, muſt I, becauſe private, periſh for want of juſtice, when I hope you will grant, I ſhould not famiſh for want of pitie? Private men that were to pay money, I hope were looked after, why not pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men, that were to receive? If the receiving were a publick advantage, ſurely paying was a publick duty. But did no private men finde a redreſſe from you, for almoſt 12 months? Nay did no private men in this time receive extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie gratuities, which I alſo was one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended for, though as yet I want my pay? you can tell. Had you not one half houres time to conſider my deep extremities, able, if I, and they were well known, to move a ſtone, what? not ſo little time for me? that have ſpent dayes, nights, months, yeers, ſo many, ſo much time to ſupport that power and wealth by which you were to relieve me? I have obſerved a Motto about your <hi>Engliſh</hi> Coynes, <hi>Juſtitia ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat thronum,</hi> the want of this is the mother of all the changes and revolutions in the world, the corruption of this unſetled the Kingdome at firſt; the corruption of this pull'd down your ſelves; and the corruption of this, if not ſeaſonably looked into, will ruine all. Were they not your ſolemn profeſſions at your firſt ſitting, that having felt the weight of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98599:23"/>and injuſtice from others, the bent of your counſels and actions ſhould be, that Juſtice might be impartially done to all? Did you not with profeſſions to this purpoſe, fiſh for hearts, and catch thouſands? and could you ſo eaſily neglect the doing of juſtice to one of your faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervants, eſpecially when it would have gotten you the additionall honour of another vertue, <hi>viz:</hi> ſhewing of pitie? But you were bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied about the Publick; Be it ſo, yet me thinks, you could not but ſee, what I heard a mean man once obſerve, that the adminiſtration of private juſtice is a publick good; how elſe could that be true, that <hi>Juſtitia firmat thronum,</hi> But I was a ſtranger? I pray you how many of your own Nation betrayed you, whileſt I ſtood firm? How many of them would have betrayed you, when they could not; whereas I would not, when I could, though I had ſtrong tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? How few did you better ſervice moving in no higher a ſphear? How many forſook you upon eaſie trials, when I ſtuck to you againſt all? If it be a granted principle that I muſt be ſlighted, becauſe a ſtranger, yet ſure I ſhould have been regarded, becauſe a good ſervant: what could you imagine I ſhould do? I had ſpent, ſold, and pawned, all that I had, except what I onely mean to part with, when I part with life. I was, and am ſtill, as deeply plunged into debt, as my friends would give me leave.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98599:24"/>I had a wife and children, which though you would not look after, yet I could not ſo eaſily forget, how did you think I ſhould ſubſiſt? How ſhould theſe be fed? I had no skill to trade, no are to begge, no heart to rob; did you ayme that my miſerable neceſſities ſhould force me that which my ſoul loaths? Did I hate in my heart, forbear in my practiſe, reſtrain in my Souldiers, all kinde of plundering, even then when we had taken Towns, and might have done it under the colour of war, all which ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not a little to your honour, that you had ſuch a ſervant; And could that be thought good dealing, to neceſſitate me, for want of my deſerved pay, to raiſe proviſion for my deare wife and children, by my violence to others: But you knew not my wants, one of your num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who, it is to be ſuppoſed knew your mind, ſaid I was a private man, and you would not look upon my Petition, as much as to ſay, you would not know them. Beſides when one had done good ſervice, to a State long ſince, you know that a voluntary inquirie was made; what honour had been done to the man for all this? And indeed what honour? yea what ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice? yea what injuſtice, rather? For, alas, how can I ſay leſſe, under the ſenſe of ſuch a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing condition; the very grief whereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beyond the anguiſh of all my wounds, hath lately thrown me into an extreme ſickneſſe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98599:24"/>and that to the edge of my grave: I ſhall much wonder, if now at length, upon the view of your failings, I ſhould not ſee my redreſſe, and know my helpers, which accordingly ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I ſhall not fail to give the world as thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a teſtimony as in this I have giventrue.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Roſworme.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
